<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondence of Catherine the Great - placeography</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2025-02-27" who="djakacki">New TEI-All structure created (Jakacki) </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <listEvent xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <event when-custom="1789-09-30" xml:id="akker01">
    <label>Taking of Belgorod on the Dniester (Белгород Днестровский)/Akkerman
			(Аккерман)</label>
    <note type="editorial">Cossack ataman M.I. Platov had been sent to negotiate with the
			Ottomans in the fortress, but when the negotiations were dragged on and the Turks shot
			at the Russian, Potemkin had time to come up with reinforcements, bombard the fortress,
			and force the three-tailed pasha Taifur to surrender, alongside his garrison of
			3,000.</note>
    <bibl><author>V.S. Lopatin</author>, <title ref="works.xml#pot01">Ekaterina II i G.A.
				Potemkin</title>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 888</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1789-05" xml:id="allia01">
    <label>Renewal of the alliance between Austria and Russia</label>
    <note type="editorial">Catherine and Joseph renewed their alliance, first contracted in May
			1781, by the same means as before: an exchange of autograph letters, rather than a
			formal treaty. Joseph's formal letter was dated 20 May, Catherine's 30 May 1789.</note>
    <bibl><title ref="works.xml#jos01">Joseph II. und Katharina von Russland</title>, <biblScope unit="page">pp. 333-36</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1781-05" xml:id="allia02">
    <label>Alliance between Austria and Russia</label>
    <bibl><author>Isabel de Madariaga</author>, <title level="a" ref="works.xml#madariaga02">'The Secret Austro-Russian Treaty of 1781'</title>, <title level="j">The Slavonic
				and East European Review</title><biblScope unit="volume">38</biblScope>.<biblScope unit="issue">90</biblScope>
				(<date>December 1969</date>), <biblScope unit="page">114-45</biblScope></bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1775" to="1783" xml:id="ameri01">
    <label>American Revolution</label>
  </event>
  <event from-custom="1765-08-04" to-custom="1787-04-30" xml:id="anglo01">
    <label>Anglo-Russian commercial treaty of 1765</label>
    <note type="editorial">Signed 4/15 April 1765. Permitted to lapse by William Pitt in April
			1787.</note>
  </event>
  <event from-custom="1793-03-14" to-custom="1793-03-25" xml:id="anglo02">
    <label>Anglo-Russian commercial treaty of 14/25 March 1793.</label>
    <note type="editorial">Revolutionary France under the Convention declared war on Great
			Britain on 21 January/1 February 1793. Six days later, Russia began negotiating a new
			alliance with Britain's envoy to St. Petersburg. <ref target="people.xml#vor01">Semen
				Vorontsov</ref> concluded a renewal of the <ref target="events.xml#ang01">treaty of
				1765</ref> on 14/25 March 1793 in London. It was accompanied by a second treaty: the
			two sides agreed to support one another in fighting France, to make peace only jointly,
			to exclude all commerce with France, and to prevent France from trading with neutral
			nations. This final provision contradicted Catherine's former policy of <ref target="arm01">Armed Neturality</ref>.</note>
    <bibl><author>Isabel de Madariaga</author>, <title ref="works.xml#rus03">Russia in the Age
				of Catherine the Great</title>, <biblScope unit="page">pp. 442-43</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1780" to="1783" xml:id="armed01">
    <label>Catherine's policy of Armed Neutrality</label>
    <bibl><author>Isabel de Madariaga</author>, <title>Britain, Russia and the Armed Neutrality
				of 1780</title> (<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>, <date>1963</date>)</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1761-12-25" xml:id="ascen01">
    <label>Peter III's ascension to the throne as emperor</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1762-06-28" xml:id="ascen02">
    <label>Catherine's ascension to the throne</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1763-10-05" xml:id="augus01">
    <label>Death of Augustus III, King of Poland</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1788-08" to="1788-11" xml:id="banat01">
    <label>Ottoman invasion of the Banat</label>
    <note type="editorial">The Ottoman army led by the Grand Vizir posed a very serious threat
			to Joseph II when he invaded this Habsburg territory, and Joseph sought a way of freeing
			himself from the Russian alliance that had drawn him into the war. By the end of 1788,
			though, the Ottomans had retreated from the region.</note>
    <bibl><author>Derek Beales</author>, <title ref="works.xml#joseph02">Joseph II</title>,
				<biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">pp.
			572-74</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1778-07" to="1779-05" xml:id="bavar01">
    <label>War of the Bavarian Succession</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1789-09-15" to="1789-10-08" xml:id="belgr01">
    <label>Siege of Belgrade</label>
    <note type="editorial">Ended in an Austrian victory under the leadership of General Laudon.
			Catherine's correspondent, the <ref target="lig01">prince de Ligne</ref>, was
			present.</note>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-11-03" xml:id="bende01">
    <label>Surrender of Bender to Prince Potemkin</label>
    <note type="editorial">Potemkin's army had surrounded the fortress of Bender from 29 October
			1789. When his army was preparing to storm the fortress, on 3 November, the garrison
			surrendered unconditionally. The Russians took the fortress, 300 pieces of artillery,
			extensive supplies; the garrison of 16,000 people, including a three-tailed pasha and
			Ahmet Pasha, and up to 22,000 inhabitants. Only 10 Russians were wounded in the taking
			of Bender. Potemkin announced the victory to Catherine on 4 November with the words:
			'Вот, матушка Всемилостивейшая Государыня, и Бендеры у ног Ваших' ('Here, little mother,
			All-Merciful Sovereign, Bender too is at your feet'). Catherine rewarded Potemkin with a
			laurel crown made of gold. For their epistolary exchange on the topic, see Catherine's
			letter to Potemkin of <ref target="letter-88">25 November 1789</ref>.</note>
    <bibl><author>Petrov</author>, <title ref="works.xml#vtoray01">Vtoraya turetskaya
				voina</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">pp.
				84-88</biblScope>.</bibl>
    <bibl><title ref="works.xml#eka01">Ekaterina II i G.A. Potemkin</title>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 381</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1744-06-29" xml:id="betro01">
    <label>Catherine's betrothal to the future Peter III</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1763" xml:id="biron01">
    <label>Restoration of Ernst Johann von Biron as duke of Courland</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1767-05-07" xml:id="birth01">
    <label>Birth of Princess Frederica Charlotte of Prussia</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1789-01" to="1790-12" xml:id="braba01">
    <label>Brabant Revolution</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1766" xml:id="brita01">
    <!-- each event should have a <label> -->
    <label>Commercial treaty with Great Britain</label>
    <!-- notes and bibliographic references optional -->
    <note type="editorial">In 1766 Catherine agreed to a commercial treaty with Great Britain
			but stopped short of a full military alliance.</note>
    <listBibl>
      <bibl><author>Rodger, NAM</author> (<date>2005</date>). <!-- you could include a @ref on title to point to this in the works.xml file -->
				<title>Command of the Ocean: A Naval History of Britain, 1649–1815</title>.
					<publisher>W. W. Norton &amp; Company</publisher>. <idno type="ISBN">978-0-393-06050-8</idno>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 328</biblScope><note type="editorial">bibliographic notes</note></bibl>
    
			<!-- more optional bibl elements -->
		</listBibl>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-09-13" xml:id="cause01">
    <label>Battle at Căuşeni</label>
    <note type="editorial">Colonel Platov led some Cossacks from the left bank of the Dniepr and
			a detachment of mounted Jägers in an attack on the Ottoman entrenchments. Some 700
			Ottoman troops were killed and 100 taken prisoner, including the officer in command at
			Căuşeni, the Beylerbey of Anatolia.</note>
    <bibl><author>Petrov</author>, <title ref="works.xml#vtoray01">Vtoraya turetskaya
				voina</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">pp.
				76-77</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from-custom="1770-06-24" to-custom="1770-06-26" xml:id="chesm01">
    <label>Battle of Chesme</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1762-09-22" xml:id="coron01">
    <label>Catherine II's coronation</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1762-06-28" xml:id="coupd01">
    <label>Catherine's coup d'état</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1787" xml:id="crime01">
    <label>Catherine's journey to the Crimea</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1773-10-08" to="1774-03-05" xml:id="dider01">
    <label>Denis Diderot's visit to St. Petersburg</label>
  </event>
  <event from-custom="1772-07-27" to-custom="1772-08-28" xml:id="focsa01">
    <label>Focșani Congress</label>
    <label>Фокшанский конгресс</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-07-21" xml:id="focsa02">
    <label>Battle of Focșani</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1789" to="1799" xml:id="frenc01">
    <label>The French Revolution</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-09-14" xml:id="gadzh01">
    <label>Taking of Gadzhibei Fortress (Odessa)</label>
    <note type="editorial">The attack was led by José de Ribas. Over 200 Ottoman soldiers were
			killed; the 66-person garrison surrendered with 12 canon, 8 standards, 2 flags, and
			various military stores. Russian losses were minimal.</note>
    <bibl><author>Petrov</author>, <title ref="works.xml#vtoray01">Vtoraya turetskaya
				voina</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">pp.
				77-79</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1788-12-19" xml:id="gangu01">
    <label>Victory at Gangura, near Bender, in Moldova.</label>
    <note type="editorial">The commanding general was <ref target="people.xml#kam01">Mikhail
				Kamensky</ref>. It was a very bloody victory, and a large number of civilians were
			slaughtered.</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1700" to="1721" xml:id="great01">
    <label>Great Northern War</label>
    <note type="editorial">Between Peter I and Charles XII of Sweden. Despite initial defeats,
			Russia's victory asserted the empire's place as a major player on the European
			stage.</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1773-09" to="1774-04" xml:id="grimm01">
    <label>Friedrich Melchior Grimm's first visit to St. Petersburg</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1777" xml:id="gusta01">
    <label>Gustav III of Sweden's visit to St. Petersburg</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1772-08" xml:id="gusta02">
    <label>Gustav III's of Sweden's coup d'état</label>
    <note type="editorial">Established absolute monarchy in Sweden, much to the chagrin of
			Russia, which relied on the factionalism of the Swedish parliament to keep this Northern
			neighbour weak.</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1770" to="1771-01" xml:id="henry01">
    <label>Prince Henry of Prussia's first visit to St. Petersburg</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1776" xml:id="henry02">
    <label>Prince Henry of Prussia's second visit to St. Petersburg</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1788-07-06" xml:id="hogla01">
    <label>Battle of Hogland</label>
    <label xml:lang="ru">Гогландское сражение</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1763-02-15" xml:id="huber01">
    <label>Treaty of Hubertusberg</label>
    <note type="editorial">One of two treaties concluding the Seven Years' War, along with the
			Treaty of Paris. Signed by Prussia, Austria, and Saxony, the treaty restored more or
			less the pre-war territorial status quo.</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1768" xml:id="inocu01">
    <label>Catherine's inoculation against smallpox</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1790-12-11" xml:id="izmai01">
    <label>Taking of <ref target="places.xml#izm01">Izmail</ref></label>
  </event>
  <event when="1773" xml:id="karol01">
    <label>Karoline of Hesse-Darmstadt's visit to St. Petersburg</label>
    <note type="editorial">The landgrafin visited with her three daughters in order to arrange
			the marriage of Wilhelmine, the future Grand Duchess Natalya Alekseevna, to Grand Duke
			Paul. The group traveled via Berlin, assuring themselves of Frederick II's support,
			before being taken on three Russian navy ships from Lübeck to Reval (Tallinn). They met
			Catherine at Gatchina, and Paul joined the party on the way to Tsarskoe Selo
					(<bibl><author>McGrew</author>, <title ref="works.xml#mcgrew01">Paul I</title>,
					<biblScope unit="page">pp. 83-84</biblScope></bibl>).</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1788-09" xml:id="khoti01">
    <label>Taking of Khotin</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-05-31" xml:id="kirob01">
    <label>Battle at Kiro</label>
    <note type="editorial">Small skirmish opening the land campaign in Swedish Finland in 1789.
			Mikhelson attacked 1000 Swedes with about 6000 Russian troops. Cossacks and Bashkirs in
			Russian service chased the defeated and frightened Swedes.</note>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1774-07-10" xml:id="kuchu01">
    <label>Treaty of Kuchuk Kainardzhi</label>
    <note type="editorial">Concluded Catherine's first Russo-Turkish War (1768-1774). Negotiated
			by Field-Marshal Petr Rumyantsev. The Russians received their highest demands: although
			they lost Ochakov, they gained Kerch, Yenikale, Kinburg, and the coastline between the
			Bug and Dniepr Rivers. They also obtained shipping rights on the Black Sea; although
			they could not keep warships, they were not prevented from building a battle fleet or
			from arming merchant ships. The Ottomans were also to pay Russia 4.5 million rubles of
			indemnity.</note>
    <bibl><author>Isabel de Madariaga</author>, <title ref="works.xml#rus03">Russia in the Age
				of Catherine the Great</title>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 235</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1773-10-10" when-custom="1773-09-29" xml:id="marri01">
    <label>Marriage of Grand Duke Paul to Grand Duchess Natalya Alekseevna (née Wilhelmine of
			Hesse-Darmstadt).</label>
    <note type="editorial">The marriage was initially a happy one, with Catherine writing of her
			son to Mme Bielke on 6 October 1773: 'Le voilà donc en ménage; il prétend vivre
			bourgeoisement, il ne quitte pas d'un pas son épouse, et cela fait la plus belle amitié
			du monde. Dieu veuille qu'elle soit de durée, car, comme dit l'autre, la vie de l'homme
			est longue' (<bibl><title ref="works.xml#edition02">SIRIO</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">xiii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 361</biblScope></bibl>). But it
			quickly deteriorated with Catherine's disapproval of the grand duchess and with rumours
			that the latter was having an affair with Andrey Razumovsky.</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1776-10-07" when-custom="1776-09-26" xml:id="marri02">
    <label>Marriage of Grand Duke Paul to Grand Duchess Maria Fedorovna (née Sophie Dorothea of
			Württemberg)</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1785-06" xml:id="mosco01">
    <label>Surprise journey to Moscow</label>
    <note type="editorial">Catherine traveled to Moscow with her court and several foreign
			ambassadors, whom she hoped would write home favourably about what they saw. This was an
			unexpected extension of a tour to inspect the construction of a canal between the Baltic
			and the Volga, visiting Lake Ladoga and Vyshnii Volochek. Catherine, her court, and the
			ambassadors produced several jocular works of society literature relating to the
			journey.</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1776-04-26" when-custom="1776-04-15" xml:id="natal01">
    <label>Death of Grand Duchess Natalya Alekseevna</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1788-12-17" when-custom="1788-12-06" xml:id="ochak01">
    <label>Taking of Ochakov</label>
    <note type="editorial">After the Turkish navy had been defeated near Ochakov on 1 July 1788,
			Grigory Potemkin's army began a siege of the fortress. Aleksandr Suvorov was wounded in
			the neck during a skirmish outside Ochakov on 27 July. Although Potemkin had planned to
			storm the fortress since November, bad weather had hindered operations. In the
			successful attack on 6 December, some 9,500 Turks and about 1,000 Russians were killed.
			Catherine rewarded Potemkin with a first-class order of St. George, a diamond-studded
			sword, 100,000 rubles, and the famous phrase in her letter of 16 December 1788: 'За ушки
			взяв обеими руками, мысленно тебя цалую, друг мой сердечный Князь Григорий
			Александрович' ('taking you by their ears with both hands, I kiss you in my thoughts, my
			dear friend Prince Grigory Aleksandrovich'. (<bibl><author>A.N. Petrov</author>, <title ref="works.xml#vtoray01">Vtoraya turetskaya voina v tsarstvovanie imperatritsy
					Ekateriny II. 1787-1791 gg.</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">i</biblScope>,
					<biblScope unit="page">pp. 183-204</biblScope></bibl>.)</note>
  </event>
  <event from-custom="1789-07-14" to-custom="1789-07-16" xml:id="oland01">
    <label>Battle of Öland</label>
    <note type="editorial">According to Aleksandr Brückner, neither the Russians nor the Swedes
			emerged victorious from this battle. Both sides were unprepared and hesitant to engage
			in full battle. The Russians achieved their aim of uniting Admiral <ref target="people.xml#chi01">Chichagov</ref>'s fleet with Vice-Admiral <ref target="people.xml#koz01">Kozlyaninov</ref>'s on 21 July/1 August. Yet it was the
			Swedes, not the Russians, who viewed the battle as successful enough to merit a 'Te
			Deum'. <ref target="people.xml#khr01">Khrapovitsky</ref>'s <ref target="works.xml#dne01">diary</ref> entry on the matter highlight Catherine's frustration with her
			admirals' failure to take offensive action: recording the report received on 6 August
			1789, he added Catherine's reponse: 'Замечено, что не хотел сам Чичагов драться, желая
			лучше охранять берега Лифляндские, хотя ему точно предписано искать и атаковать
			неприятеля. Je crois que tout le monde est d'accord avec le Roi de Suède. Le Prince de
			Nassau n'a presque rien fait. Pouchkin est dans l'inaction. Дсд. [досада]. Пчт. слз. н.
			глзх. [почти слезы на глазах].' ('Commented that Chichagov himself did not want to
			fight, preferring to guard the coast of Lifland, although he was expressly ordered to
			seek out and attack the enemy. I think everyone is in agreement with the King of Sweden.
			Prince Nassau has done almost nothing. Pouchkin is inactive. Annoyance. Almost tears in
			her eyes'). (<bibl><author>Brückner</author>, <title ref="works.xml#voinar01">Voina
					Rossii so Shvetsiei</title>, <biblScope unit="page">pp. 190-94</biblScope></bibl>;
					<bibl><author>Khrapovitsky</author>, <title ref="works.xml#dne01">Dnevnik</title>, <biblScope unit="page">p. 302</biblScope></bibl>.)</note>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-06" xml:id="paros01">
    <label>Battle of Parosalmi</label>
    <note type="editorial">Catherine's secretary Khrapovitsky noted on 7 June 1789: '<ref target="people.xml#mus02">Гр. В. П. М. Пушкин</ref> [граф Валентин Платонович Мусин]
			из Вильманстранда от 5 Июня прислал неприятное донесение, что Михельсон 1-го Июня
			выступя из Христины, в 3 часа по полуночи, со всеми войсками дошел до переправы,
			называемой Паросальма и тут претерпел знатный урон; войска отступили в Христину.
			Паросальма в шести верстах от Сант-Михеля. Бар. <ref target="people.xml#spr01">Спренгпортен</ref> весь изранен. Двадцать семь лет такого известия не получала!'
				('<ref target="people.xml#mus02">Ct V.P.M. Pushkin</ref> [Count Valentin Platonovich
			Musin] sent from Vilmanstrand on 5 June the unpleasant news that Mikhelson on the 1st of
			June, leaving Khristina, at 3 a.m., with all his troops arrived at the crossing called
			Parosalma and there suffered serious losses. The troops retreated into Khristina.
			Parosalma is 6 versts from Sant-Mikhel. Bar. Sprengporten (Baron Sprengtporten) is
			wounded all over. I (Catherine) have never received such news in twenty seven years!'
					(<bibl><title ref="works.xml#dne01">Dnevnik A.V. Khrapovitskago</title>,
					<biblScope unit="page">p. 288</biblScope></bibl>.) </note>
  </event>
  <event when="1772" xml:id="parti01">
    <label>First partition of Poland</label>
    <note type="editorial">The partition treaty between Prussia and Russia was signed on 6/17
			February 1772; Austria joined on 25 July/5 August 1772.</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1788-12-29" xml:id="prote01">
    <label>Protest against the Third Resolution</label>
    <note type="editorial">On 29 December 1788, in the midst of the Regency Crisis, a group of
			Opposition Lords filed a protest against the Third Resolution, which was passed in the
			House of Lords and determined that the Lords and Commons 'should determine on the Means
			whereby the Royal Assent may be given in Parliament to such Bill as may be passed by the
			Two Houses of Parliament, respecting the Exercise of the Powers and Authorities of the
			Crown, in the Name and on the Behalf of the King during the Continuance of His Majesty's
			present Indisposition.' (The text of the resolution and of the protest may be found <ref target="http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.aspx?compid=116844">here</ref>.)
			Catherine supported the protest, which insisted on a regency headed by the <ref target="people.xml#geo03">prince of Wales</ref>, as royal authority should not be
			exercised by Parliament alone. <ref target="people.xml#har01">James Harris</ref>, first
			earl of Malmesbury and Catherine's old enemy (for his opposition to her policy of Armed
			Neutrality and for his arrangement of an alliance between Britain and Prussia), signed
			the protest, thus marking a move away from <ref target="people.xml#pit01">Pitt</ref>,
			Catherine's opponent.</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1764" xml:id="pruss01">
    <label>Russo-Prussian Alliance</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1780" xml:id="pruss02">
    <label>Russo-Prussian alliance lapsed</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1773-09" to="1774-09" xml:id="pugac01">
    <label>Pugachev Rebellion</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1774-09" xml:id="pugac02">
    <label>Pugachev caught</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1788-10" to="1789-02" xml:id="regen01">
    <label>Regency crisis</label>
    <note type="editorial">When George III fell gravely ill and fell victim to bouts of madness
			in late October and early November 1788, the dissolute prince of Wales (the future
			George IV) was proposed as regent. His political support came from Charles James Fox;
			George III's prime minister, William Pitt, opposed the plan for a regency and supported
			Queen Charlotte instead. Hoping to do remove Pitt from power and thus defeat his
			anti-Russian policies, Catherine strongly supported Fox and the proponents of a
			regency.</note>
    <bibl><author>T.C.W. Blanning and Carl Haase</author>, <title level="a">'George III,
				Hannover and the Regency Crisis'</title>, in <title level="m">Knights Errant and
				True Englishmen: British Foreign Policy 1600-1800</title>, ed. by <editor>Jeremy
				Black</editor> (<pubPlace>Edinburgh</pubPlace>: <publisher>John Donald</publisher>,
				<date>1989</date>, <biblScope unit="page">pp. 135-50</biblScope>.</bibl>
    <bibl><author/>, <title>The Regency Crisis and the Whigs, 1788-9</title>
				(<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>: <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>,
				<date>1963</date>)</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1790-07-27" xml:id="reich01">
    <label>Treaty of Reichenbach</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-09-11" xml:id="rymni01">
    <label>Battle of Rymnik</label>
    <note type="editorial">For this victory over the Turks, Russian General <ref target="people.xml#suv01">Aleksandr Suvorov</ref> received a diamond snuffbox and
			the title of count of the Holy Roman Empire from <ref target="people.xml#jos01">Joseph
				II</ref>. He received the title of count, the surname of 'Rymniksky', and a
			diamond-studded sword. <ref target="people.xml#cat01">Catherine</ref> sent a valuable
			snuffbox and a diamond-studded sword to the Austrian general, the <ref target="people.xml#cob01">prince of Saxe-Cobourg</ref>. Joseph II made him a
			field-marshal.</note>
    <bibl><author>Petrov</author>, <title ref="works.xml#vtoray01">Vtoraya turetskaya
				voina</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">pp.
				59-75</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1754" to="1763" xml:id="seven01">
    <label>Seven Years' War</label>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1789-08-13" xml:id="svens01">
    <label>First Battle of Svensksund/Rochensalm</label>
    <note type="editorial">The Russian Admiral Kruse attacked the Swedish flotilla in the
			Svensksund, at the mouth of the Kymi River at Kotka on the Gulf of Finland, with greater
			numbers of ships, but he was pushed back by the Swedes under Admiral Ehrensvärd, who
			occupied a more advantegous position in the strait. Prince Karl Friedrich von
			Nassau-Siegen then brought reinforcements: although the Swedes had almost no ammunition
			left, Gustav III ordered Ehrensvärd to attack. The Russians captured 33 Swedish ships
			and forced the Swedes to flee to the fortress of Svartsholm. Ehrensvärd told Gustav: 'I
			have the honour of informing your Majesty that you have no longer a coast flotilla'.
			Although the king did not blame Ehrensvärd for the loss and graciously awarded to him
			the Order of the Sword, usually given only to victorious military leaders, the admiral
			retired. This naval success then allowed the Russian to land in Sweden, to capture the
			fortress of Hogbars, and then to destroy the rest of the Swedish flotilla at Barö
			Sound.</note>
    <bibl><author>Robert Nisbet Bain</author>, <title ref="works.xml#gustav01">Gustavus III and
				His Contemporaries</title>, <biblScope unit="volume">ii</biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">pp. 87-88</biblScope>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1789" xml:id="swedi01">
    <label>Swedish diet of 1789</label>
    <note type="editorial">This was the first time that Gustav III of Sweden had called together
			the Riksdag since 1786. It resulted in a new change in government structure in the
			king's favour.</note>
    <bibl><author>Brückner</author>, <title ref="works.xml#konfed01">'Konfederatsiya v Anyala v
				1788 godu'</title>.</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1788" to="1790" xml:id="swedi02">
    <label>Russo-Swedish War</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1779-05-13" xml:id="tesch01">
    <label>Peace of Teschen</label>
    <note type="editorial">Peace treaty that ended the War of the Bavarian Succession, brought
			about by Catherine and considered a great diplomatic victory for her.</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1779-03" to="1779-05" xml:id="tesch02">
    <label>Congress of Teschen</label>
    <note type="editorial">Congress which culminated in the signing of the Peace treaty of
			Teschen</note>
  </event>
  <event to="1791" from="1788" xml:id="tripl01">
    <label>Triple alliance between Great Britain, Prussia, and the United Provinces</label>
    <note type="editorial">Designed by William Pitt the Younger</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1768" to="1774" xml:id="turki01">
    <label>First Russo-Turkish War</label>
  </event>
  <event from-custom="1787-08-13" to="1792" xml:id="turki02">
    <label>Second Russo-Turkish War</label>
    <note type="editorial">Began with the Ottoman declaration of war on Russia on 13 August
			1787.</note>
  </event>
  <event when-custom="1782-04-08" xml:id="ustav01">
    <label>Police Ordinance</label>
    <note>Called the 'Устав благочиния, или полицейский', this legal document set up the Russian
			police system, listed punishments for various offences, and offered guiding moral
			principles for Russian subjects.</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1767" xml:id="volga01">
    <label>Catherine's journey down the Volga, during which she and her courtiers translated
			Marmontel's 'Bélisaire' into Russian.</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1657" xml:id="wehla01">
    <label>Treaty of Wehlau signed by the Brandenburg-Prussian and Polish-Lithuanian envoys in
			Wehlau</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1748-10-18" xml:id="aixla01">
    <label>Treaty of Aix-la-Chappelle (Treaty of Aachen)</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q156086</bibl>
    <note>Ended the War of Austrian Succession</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="allia03">
    <label>Alliance between Sweden and UK</label>
    <note>Often referred to as "Gegu"</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="allia04">
    <label>Alliance between France and the United Provinces (Holland)</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="assas01">
    <label>Assassination of Gustave III</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1771-07-06" to="1772-04-08" xml:id="austr01">
    <label>Secret treaty between Austria and the Ottomans in which Austria received land concessions and the Ottomans received subsidies</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1779" xml:id="aynal01">
    <label>Treaty of Aynalıkavak</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q7836974</bibl>
    <note>Catherine refers to it as the Convention d'Aly-Kavak ; treaty entered into b/w Russia and Ottomans intended to resolve ongoing conflict over Crimea</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="basel01">
    <label>Peace Treaty between Prussia and France</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="belgr02">
    <label>Treaty of Belgrade</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1752" to="1754" xml:id="bouff01">
    <label>Querelle des Bouffons</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q186899</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1772-10-29" to="1773-05-09" xml:id="bucha01">
    <label>Bucharest peace negotiations</label>
    <note>as resumed Focsani congress</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="coron02">
    <label>Coronation of King Louis XVI</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="crime02">
    <label>Annexation of Crimea</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="cullo01">
    <label>Battle of Culloden, Scotland</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="damie01">
    <label>Battle at the Damietta Castle</label>
    <note>under the command of Panaioti Aleksiano</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="decla01">
    <label>France declares war on Austria</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1792" to="1797" xml:id="first01">
    <label>War of the First Coalition - first period of the French Revolutionary wars</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="fleet01">
    <label>Catherine set off to Peterhof on her yacht 'Saint Catherine' to inspect her fleet in the Gulf of Finland</label>
    <note type="source">as noted in Correspondance de Falconet avec Catherine II, 1767-1778, avec une introduction et des notes par Louis Réau.</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1775-04-01" to="1775-05-30" xml:id="flour01">
    <label>Flour War, Guerre des farines</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1635316</bibl>
    <note>Riots in France following the rise in grain prices</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="fonta01">
    <label>Treaty of Fontainbleau</label>
    <note>between Joseph II and the States-General of the United Provinces</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="frenc02">
    <label>Franco-Russian commercial treaty</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1764" xml:id="hetma01">
    <label>Elimination of the Cossack Hetmanate</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1790-02-20" xml:id="josep01">
    <label>Death of Joseph II</label>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="giurg01">
    <label>Truce of Giurgiu</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1771" xml:id="kafa01">
    <label>Battle of Kafa</label>
    <note>WRONG FORMAT CODE, ALSO IN LETTER XML</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="kagul01">
    <label>Battle of Kagul</label>
    <note type="source">as noted in Correspondance de Falconet avec Catherine II, 1767-1778, avec une introduction et des notes par Louis Réau.</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1794-03-24" to="1794-11-16" xml:id="kosci01">
    <label>Kościuszko Uprising</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q849176</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1770-07-07" xml:id="larga01">
    <label>Battle of Larga</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2456110</bibl>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="leipz01">
    <label>Student unrest in Leipzig, Fedor Ushakov was involved</label>
    <note type="source">letter-01164</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="marri03">
    <label>Marriage of Mme Clotilde</label>
    <note>POSSIBLE DUPLICATE OF marri04</note>
    <note type="source">as noted in the correspondence between Catherine and Grimm and between Grimm and Nesselrode</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1775-08-21" xml:id="marri04">
    <label>Marriage of Mme Clotilde of France to Charles Emmanuel IV of Sardinia</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1764-07-06" xml:id="mirov01">
    <label>Mirovich Affair</label>
    <note>POSSIBLE DUPLICATE OF schli01</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1775" xml:id="mosco02">
    <label>Catherine's trip to Moscow</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1787" xml:id="mulov01">
    <label>Mulovsky expedition</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q6934320</bibl>
    <note>expedition planned by Catherine II that never occurred due to the second Russo-Turkish war</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1784" to="1785" xml:id="neckl01">
    <label>Affair of the Queen's Necklace</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q465744</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1743-08-30" xml:id="abotre01">
    <label>Treaty of Abo</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1141485</bibl>
    <note>Sometimes called Neustadt and Abo or Treaty of Turku; peace treaty signed between Russian Empire and Sweden in Turku (Abo) in 1743</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="norma01">
    <label>Norman Conquest</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1770-02-01" to="1770-06-30" xml:id="orlov01">
    <label>Orlov Revolt</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q783310</bibl>
    <note>Russian historiorgaphy recognises two events: Peloponnesus Revolt (Пелопонесское восстание) and the First Archipelago Expedition of the Russian Fleet (Первая архипелагская экспедиция). Part of the first Russo-Turkish War (1768-1774).</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1573" to="1764" xml:id="pacta01">
    <label>Pacta conventa</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1095146</bibl>
    <note>contractual agreement entered into between the Polish nation and the newly elected king upon his "free election"</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="paler01">
    <label>Palermo Revolt</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1718-07-21" xml:id="passa01">
    <label>Treaty of Passarowitz</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q211395</bibl>
  </event>
  <event from="1772-11-06" to="1772-11-08" xml:id="patra01">
    <label>Battle of Patras</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q2040773</bibl>
    <note>under the command of Michael Konyaev</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1762-04-24" xml:id="peter01">
    <label>Treaty of St Petersburg</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q689032</bibl>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="plagu01">
    <label>Moscow plague</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1771-09-15" xml:id="plagu02">
    <label>Moscow plague riots</label>
  </event>
  <event from="1709-06-27" to="1709-07-08" xml:id="polta01">
    <label>Battle of Poltava</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q152486</bibl>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="pregn01">
    <label>Grand Duchess Natalya's pregnancy</label>
    <note type="source">as noted in the correspondence between Catherine II and Grimm</note>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="pruss03">
    <label>Prussian invasion of Holland</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1711-07-23" xml:id="pruth01">
    <label>Treaty of the Pruth</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q313349</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1777-10-16" xml:id="sarat01">
    <label>The defeat and surrender of British General John Burgoyne at Saratoga</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1764-07-05" xml:id="schli01">
    <label>Rebellion</label>
    <note>Failed attempt to free Ivan VI from the Sclissemburg Fortress, his death</note>
  </event>
  <event from="1790-09-08" to="1790-09-09" xml:id="tendr01">
    <label>Battle of Tendra</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q4438427</bibl>
  </event>
  <event xml:id="utrec01">
    <label>Peace of Utretcht</label>
    <note>peace treaties signed to end the War of the Spanish Succession</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1790-08-14" xml:id="varal01">
    <label>Treaty of Värälä</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q1456660</bibl>
    <note>Treaty between Russia and Sweden that concludd the Russo-Swedish War</note>
  </event>
  <event when="1648-10-24" xml:id="westph01">
    <label>Peace of Westphalia</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q150995</bibl>
  </event>
  <event when="1782-08-07" xml:id="monum01">
    <label>Opening of the monument to Peter the Great in Saint-Petersburg</label>
  </event>
  <event when="1792-01-09" xml:id="jassy01">
    <label>Treaty of Jassy</label>
    <bibl>https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q122442</bibl>
    <note>Ended Second Russo-Turkish war (1787-1791)</note>
  </event>
</listEvent>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
